Inventory of the Center for Libertarian Studies records
Hoover Institution Archives
Center for Libertarian Studies records
1961-1986
1977-1984
96043
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (1.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, conference papers, draft journal articles, proposals, agenda, and financial records relating to libertarianism.
Center for Libertarian Studies.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Center for Libertarian Studies (CLS), an American non-profit organization for the promotion of libertarianism and libertarian research, was founded in 1976 by Murray N. Rothbard and Burton S. Blumert. The organization developed from the Libertarian Scholars Conferences and was headquartered in New York, New York, where most of its early conferences were held. The organization later moved to Burlingame, California.
The Center for Libertarian Studies held events such as conferences, seminars, symposia, dinners, and other meetings where libertarian scholars spoke, including Murray N. Rothbard, Llewelyn (Lew) Rockwell, Jr., Dom Armentano, Earl Ravenal, Henry Mark Holzer, Wendy McElroy, Randy Barnett, and Richard Epstein. In 1982, Rothbard and Blumert, along with Lew Rockwell, went on to found the Ludwig von Mises Institute to further libertarian research and study in Austrian economics, freedom, and peace.
The CLS published the newsletter In Pursuit of Liberty, along with various CLS-sponsored papers, articles and monographs. The Journal of Libertarian Studies is a scholarly, peer-reviewed title that the CLS published from 1977 to 2000; after that time the Mises Institute took over the publication. Additionally, the CLS founded the Ludwig von Mises Fellowship awarding achievement in Libertarian scholarship.
Murray N. Rothbard died in 1995. Burton S. Blumert retired in 2008 and died in March 2009.
Related Collection(s)
Gottfried Haberler Papers, Hoover Institution Archives.
Libertarian Party of California Records, Hoover Institution Archives.
Mont Pèlerin Society Records, Hoover Institution Archives.
"Inventory of the private papers of Ludwig Von Mises," 1978. Stanford University Library.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes correspondence, reports, conference papers, journal articles and drafts, proposals, organizational rosters, mailing lists, agenda, ephemera, budgets and financial records, photographs, and printed matter relating to libertarianism and its socio-political impact, covering topics such as immigration, education, economics, philosophy, and non-violence.
Austrian school of economics.; Blumert, Burton S., 1929-2009.; Economics--Philosophy.; Education -- Libertarian theories, to 1982; Immigration rights.; Laissez-faire.; Libertarianism--Conferences.; Libertarianism--Research.; Libertarianism--United States.; Libertarianism.; Liberty.; Nonviolence.; Rothbard, Murray Newton, 1926-1995.; Von Mises, Ludwig, 1881-1973.
- Organizational File, 1961-1986
  Scope and Contents note
  The Board of Advisors files include correspondence, program proposals, ephemera, printed matter, appeal letters, agendas, and event planning records, along with the Speaker's Bureau and Heritage Series correspondence between Bureau staff and experts such as Earl Ravenal, Randy Barnett, Murray Rothbard, Dom Armentano, and Llewellyn (Lew) H. Rockwell, Jr.
  - Board of Advisors, 1961 September-1982 January (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Speaker's Bureau and anti-trust symposium, 1977-1982 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Heritage Series program, 1977 October-1982 September (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Printed matter and miscellaneous materials, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Conferences, Colloquia, Events, Seminars, and Symposia Materials, 1976-1984
  Includes event records such as budgets, correspondence, proposals, printed matter, conference papers, and manuscripts on CLS conferences, symposia, colloquia, dinners, and talks covering topics such as Austrian economics, philosophy, education, religion, crime and punishment, and libertarian socio-political thought. Includes papers written by CLS participants and scholars for presentation at conferences, seminars, symposia, and professional association meetings, talks and events. Topics include: "Economic History," "The State and the Medical Profession," and "Crime and Punishment."
  - Austrian Economics seminar papers, 1976 July-November (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Philosophy conferences and colloquia, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Harvard Law Conferences and Symposia, 1976 February-1979 February (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Summer Research Seminar on Opponents of Public Schooling, 1977 June 8-August 5 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 5th Annual Libertarian Conference papers, 1977 October 21-23 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
  - 8th Annual Libertarian Scholars Conference papers, 1981 June-November (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Murray N. Rothbard event files, 1982-1984
    - Events and Orange County dinner records, 1982 May-July (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - "Economic Thought from the Greeks Through the 18th Century: A Reappraisal,", 1984 February-June (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Stanford University conferences and event materials, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Includes conference proposals, agenda, and correspondence. Files also include work with the Decisions and Ethics Center at Stanford University: "On Human Rights," "On Social Science Methodology," and "Liberty and Culture," with commentator Joan Kennedy Taylor, followed by reception hosted by the Institute for Humane Studies.
    - West Coast Libertarian Studies Conference, 1980 May-July
    - "Economics: Austrian Theory and Public Policy,", 1982 April-June
    - 6th Annual Day at Stanford: "Banking and Monetary Policy,", 1983 June-August
    - 7th Annual Day at Stanford: "Capitalism and Christianity" and "Democracy in Paralysis,", 1984 October-November
  - Midwestern Libertarian Scholars, Chicago Conference materials, 1982-1984
    - Correspondence, agenda, and miscellaneous materials, 1983 January-1984 May (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Writings, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      Organized according to the original arrangement, by last name. Topics include modern libertarianism and faith, immigration, moral judgement, landlordism, liberty, and corporate freedom.
      - Cody, John V., circa 1984
      - Hudson, James L., circa 1984
      - Presley, Sharon L., circa 1982
      - Spall, Richard F., Jr., circa 1984
      - Uyl, Douglas D., circa 1984
- Study Group File, 1976-1985
  A collection of correspondence, manuscripts, and research files, using the organization's original titles where provided. Files in quotations are the title of the manuscript as orginally labeled by the organization.
  - Friedrich A. Hayek, late 1970s (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Children's Rights Project, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Education and the State, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Includes subject files such as "The Study of Liberty in Colleges and Universities," with conference materials, and correspondence with the Foundation for Economic Education, Inc. (FEE).
  - "The Birth of Transfer Society,", circa 1978 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "Explaining the Anti-War Movement, 1939-1941: The Next Assignment,", 1985 January (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Robert L. Formaini, 1981 August-1982 February (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Dr. Hans-Hermann Hoppe, 1985 February-April (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "Two Concepts of Rule by Law,", circa 1985 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Non-Violent Study Group, circa 1979-1983 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Theology and Economics, circa 1982 October-1983 January (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Photographs and other materials.
- Fellowships File, 1979-1984
  Includes correspondence and seminar presentations on libertarian rights, proposals, and grants.
  - John Gray Fellowship, 1979 December-1983 July (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Ludwig von Mises Fellowship Program, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Mises Fellowship advertisements with History of Ideas and related publications, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Mark E. Weinburg Fellowship and Grant, 1977 May-1984 August (Box-folder 4: 11)
    Includes papers and reports regarding the Weinburg grant and Weinburg's fellowship funded by the Scaife Family Charitable Trust.
- The Journal of Libertarian Studies Publication Files, 1977-1986
  Contains records such as a grant proposal, correspondence, and submissions to The Journal of Libertarian Studies. The correspondence includes letters between Murray N. Rothbard and libertarian scholars such as Charles Koch and Hans-Hermann Hoppe. Also included are reports on the Austrian Economics Newsletter (AEN).
  - Letter to Charles Koch, rejection letters, and manuscripts, 1977 February-1983 November (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984 April-1986 June (Box-folder 5: 2)